Barbara Abel Papers, 1925-1989
Sophia Smith Collection
Barbara Abel papers
1925-1989
Abel, Barbara
MS 596
4 boxes (1.5 linear ft.)
Sophia Smith Collection Smith College Northampton, MA
Public relations specialist, Columnist, Journalist, YWCA worker, Editor. The papers primarily relate to Abel's professional life and include her magazine columns for the YWCA and Community Chests and Councils of America, scripts for skits and plays, and a variety of other pieces written in the course of Abel's work as editor and publicity director for a variety of organizations.
Writer, editor, and public relations specialist Barbara Abel was born on January 5, 1895, in Elizabethtown, New York. She was the second daughter of Lucinda Pond and William H. Abel, who worked for the railroad in Chicago. Abel's mother journeyed from Chicago to Elizabethtown, the family's home in the Adirondacks, for the births of both Barbara and her sister. Barbara grew up in Chicago, but spent summers in Elizabethtown among extended family.
Educated in the public schools in Springfield, Illinois, and Kansas City, Missouri, Abel started college at Kansas University, then transferred to Northwestern University where she earned a B.A. in 1918.
Immediately after college, she worked for the Evanston, Illinois, News Index (1918-19) covering "deaths and women's clubs." In 1920 she became Publicity Secretary for the YWCA of Metropolitan Chicago.
Abel joined the staff of the YWCA of the U.S.A. as managing editor of its magazine The Womans Press in July of 1925. She began her regular column "The Press Pussy" in January 1926. An extremely popular humorous look at the YWCA, it was a regular feature of the magazine until December 1944. In addition to this monthly column, Abel wrote a wide variety of pieces for the Womans Press, as well as many skits for use at meetings, conferences, and Conventions. She and her "dearest friend of decades standing," Florence Nichols, also regularly produced delightful cartoons on YWCA themes for the Womans Press.
Abel left the National Association in the fall of 1931 to become Publicity Director for the Metropolitan Chicago YWCA. In 1945 she returned to New York City to take the job of Public Relations Director for the Community Chests and Councils of the U.S.A. (CCC) where she edited their magazine Community and developed a similarly beloved column, "The Red Feather." Among her duties at CCC was drafting annual campaign kick-off speeches for the U.S. President and Vice President. She retired from CCC in 1960. One colleague wrote at her retirement, "Now I shall have to resign myself to uninspired and turgid prose, and I don't like the idea at all."
In addition to her work for the YWCA and CCC, Abel published "light verse" in The New Yorker and other "leading magazines," and wrote articles for the National Dairy Association.
In retirement, Abel and Nichols divided their time between Abel's summer house "Bob-up" in Elizabethtown, and a small New York City apartment where Abel took on the odd freelance writing project.
She died in Elizabethtown on May 22, 1966.
In a memorial tribute, Abel's friend and colleague Henry W. Kritzmacher, described Barbara as "among the elite who foresaw sophistication in a field where the blunt, outstretched hand was rampant." He characterized her work as "a pinnacle of creative writing art which etched its message in a concise, trenchant comment that tore away sham, and in a wry humor... sold by underselling, or spanked by patting fiery heads."
The Barbara Abel Papers consist of 1.5 linear ft. and are primarily related to her professional life, dating from 1918 to 1989. Types of materials include correspondence, speeches, photographs, press releases, reports, journal and newspaper articles, magazine columns, scripts for skits and plays, speeches, writings, editorial files, and memorabilia.
The bulk of the papers date from 1926 to 1960 and consist primarily of scripts for skits and magazine columns for the YWCA and Community Chests and Councils of America. Other files give a sense of Abel's work as an editor and speech writer. Though the biographical materials are scant, her lively personality and wit are abundantly represented in the writings and correspondence.
This collection is organized into three series:
I. BIOGRAPHICAL MATERIALS, CORRESPONDENCE, AND PHOTOGRAPHS
II. WRITINGS
III. ORGANIZATIONS
The papers are open to research according to the regulations of the Sophia Smith Collection without any additional restrictions.
The Barbara Abel Papers came to the Sophia Smith Collection with the YWCA of the U.S.A. Records in 2002. The YWCA received them from Marion O. Robinson in 1977.
American wit and humor--Women authors--20th century--Sources; Charities--United States--History--20th century--Sources; Public relations--History--20th century--Sources; Women journalists--United States--Biography--Sources; Women editors--United States--Biography--Sources; Abel, Barbara; Community Chests and Councils of America--History; Womans Press; Young Women's Christian Association of the U.S.A.--History--Sources; Community Chests and Councils of America; Young Women's Christian Association of the U.S.A.
- SERIES I. BIOGRAPHICAL MATERIALS, CORRESPONDENCE, AND PHOTOGRAPHS 1918-1989, .25 linear ft.
  This series contains a small amount of general biographical material, much of it tributes written at the time of Abel's retirement from United Community Funds and Councils of America in 1966; a small amount of correspondence; and some photographs of Abel, Florence Nichols, and of productions of skits written by Barbara Abel.
- SERIES II. WRITINGS 1940-1963, .25 linear ft.
  The bulk of the writings in this series are miscellaneous personal pieces, such as poems, songs, and retirement tributes to friends. There are also a couple of general pieces on group work and social service themes. Writings done as part of Abel's work for organizations are in SERIES III.
- SERIES III. ORGANIZATIONS 1926-1966, 1 linear ft.
  This series consists of correspondence, and columns, pamphlets, skits, speeches, newsletters, conference proceedings, retirement tributes, and a variety of other pieces written in the course of Abel's work as editor and publicity director for a variety of organizations.
  Also included are materials related to volunteer efforts on behalf of membership organizations, such as the National Council of Social Work, and a variety of professional organizations and conferences of community welfare organizations.
  The series is arranged alphabetically by name of the organization.
- SERIES I. BIOGRAPHICAL MATERIALS, CORRESPONDENCE, AND PHOTOGRAPHS
  - Biographical materials
    - General 1918-89, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Florence Nichols 1927-48, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Retirement
      - Correspondence 1960 (Box 1, Folder 3)
      - Party5 Jun 1960 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, general 1941-60, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Photographs 1938-60, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
- SERIES II. WRITINGS
  - Poems and songs 1950-63, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Miscellaneous 1943-61, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - "Friends of the Family," pamphlet for local United Funds and Chests 1961 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - "Let's Work in Groups! (A Dramatic Monologue with song)" 1947, undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Tributes (mostly poems) to colleagues and friends 1940-61, undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
- SERIES III. ORGANIZATIONS
  - Community Chests and Councils of America, Inc./United Community Funds and Councils of America [United Way]
    - General 1944-61, undated (Box 1, Folder 12-13)
    - "The Red Feather" column
      - General 1947-55, undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
      - Copies of column in Community, United Community Funds and Councils of America magazine 1945-55 (Box 1, Folder 15)
      - Correspondence re ending of column 1956-57 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Retirement tributes
      - For Ralph BlanchardFeb 1960 (Box 1, Folder 17)
      - For Lois 1957 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Skits
      - Miscellaneous 1949-58, undated (Box 1, Folder 19)
      - "Follow the Leadership," for Council Leaders Conference 1961 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Speeches
      - Drafts for CCC/UCFC personnel 1958-61 (Box 1, Folder 21)
      - Drafts for President Eisenhower and Vice President Nixon 1954-58 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Community Welfare Council Leaders Conference: skit, "The Mop Up" 1959 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Council of Affiliate Agencies of the Federation of Protestant Welfare Agencies: skit, "Delegate Body (and Soul)" 1948 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Council on Foundations, 15th Annual Conference, editing of Proceedings 1964 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - National Conference of Social Work
    - Skits
      - "The Clean Up" 1938 (Box 2, Folder 5)
      - "The Gates of Paradise: a light-hearted skit on citizen participation (Volunteer Service to you!)" 1947 (Box 2, Folder 6)
      - "There Oughta Be a Law! (Citizen Participation in Words and Music)" 1948 (Box 2, Folder 7)
      - "Keep It Confidential" and "Let's Make a Study!" 1952 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Speech: "On Being and Individual Agency" 1956 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - National Council on Social Welfare: skit "Careers in Arrears" 1956-57 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - National Dairy Council: pamphlets 1950-53, undated (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - National Social Welfare Assembly: editing 1954-61 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - National Social Work Publicity Council, Chicago Chapter: "Frollies" 1935-40, undated (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - United Defense Fund
    - Skit for staff conference: "Report from Region Eight" 1951 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Speech for E.A. Roberts 1953 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Welfare Public Relations Council of Greater Chicago: skit, "Well, Well, Welfare!: a comedy skit on Citizen Participation" 1950 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - YWCA of Chicago
    - General 1935-44, undated (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - The Tower of B'Abel, publicity department newsletter 1935-44 [incomplete] (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - YWCA of the U.S.A.
    - Correspondence 1938-60 (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - Skits
      - Miscellaneous 1930-65, undated (Box 2, Folder 20-21)
      - "Committee on Space: A World Fellowship Skit with a Sense of Humus" 1959 (Box 3, Folder 1)
      - Follow the Leadership and Other Skits, Womans Press 1938 (Box 3, Folder 2)
      - "The Minute Girls Face the Future" 1965-66 (Box 3, Folder 3)
      - "Mother Earth and Her Children," as given at the conference on the cause and cure of warJan 1931 (Box 3, Folder 4)
      - "The Payoff Cometh" 1946 (Box 3, Folder 5)
      - "Personnel, Inc." 1947 (Box 3, Folder 6)
      - "Portrait of Lucinda," for World YWCA Centennial 1953-55 (Box 3, Folder 7)
      - "The Shoestring Express" and "Where do We Go From Here?," Convention 1949 (Box 3, Folder 8)
      - "Subcommittee on Brass Tacks," Convention 1952 (Box 3, Folder 9)
      - "Void if Detached: a YWCA Membership Skit in One Act" 1951 (Box 3, Folder 10)
      - "Y-olanthe" 1929 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Slide script for Convention 1961[see also YWCA of the U.S.A. Records, Slides] (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Other writings
      - Miscellaneous 1928-51, undated (Box 4, Folder 3)
      - "Knife, Fork, and Spoon River Anthologies" (short poems about YWCA staff)undated (Box 4, Folder 4)
      - The Press Pussy: miscellaneous 1942, 1988, undated (Box 4, Folder 5)
      - "The Press Pussy" column for The Womans Press 1926-44 (Box 4, Folder 6)
      - "Personnel-with a Purr" column for The YWCA Magazine 1957-58 (Box 4, Folder 7)